[Music]
yo guess who's back with a new edition
here today we're going to talk about
stretching should you do it before your
training after your training or perhaps
maybe not at all we're gonna get in that
today well the answer really depends on
the three things number one what type of
stretching are you really talking about
I'll explain a couple of different types
today number two how long you stretching
for and how long you stretching prior to
when you're gonna exercise or do your
competition and then number three how
bad your mobility or your movement or
your flexibility really is all right so
I'm gonna answer these questions very
directly and very clearly but more
importantly this gives us an opportunity
to talk about the physiology and
neurology of stretching movement in
general so that's really what the bulk
of the video is dedicated to helping you
have these answers of course but really
understanding why they're true right if
you've seen any of my videos or ever
seen any of my material really you know
that I'm really much more interested in
people understanding the why behind the
answer right the theory is if you
understand the methods or in this case
the physiology then you're never gonna
have the problem answering the question
when the scenario changes a little bit
right so don't just memorize answers
understand how things work and you'll
never have to memorize again so that's
the goal today having said that if you
wanted to zoom to the end to get the
answer this fine you can but you're
gonna be much better off taking the time
to learn some of the physiology as we go
so let's dive right into it the two
types of stretching I'm gonna talk about
really are what we'll call dynamic and
static now static is what you've
traditionally seen before right it's the
hold the hamstring stretch for 30
seconds it's hold this for two minutes
whatever right it's holding a position
in a static not moving typically at an
end range of motion or close to it now
dynamic is a little bit complicated if
you look at the research on this topic
you're gonna get confused because a lot
of the authors aren't really clear when
they're talking about static stretching
versus dynamic stretching and how that's
different than dynamic warm
all right so this is gonna actually lead
to a lot of confusion in the field if
you're trying to read stuff or you've
heard somebody else talk about that make
sure they're clarifying we're talking
about dynamic warmup or dynamic
stretching or if they even differentiate
the two so in my mind dynamic warm-up
are things like a walking active
movement right so an active bodyweight
squat while you're maybe increasing the
range of motion or how low you can get
in your squat but you're kind of doing
it through the movement itself you're
really just getting warmed up so what
you'll see there are the pros and cons
of the static versus dynamic here in a
second but you know what they are right
you know the difference in standing and
holding a hamstring stretch for two
minutes versus doing say an active
hamstring movement where you're kicking
your leg up and down okay so I'm not
going to really differentiate between
dynamic warmup and dynamic stretching at
this point though others may okay so
hopefully you get the basic idea of
dynamic movement stuff versus the static
hold and so really what we can talk
about is the pros and cons of both again
if you've seen anything I ever do I
don't talk about things being good or
bad I'd like to understand what's the
benefit what's the consequence and then
you can deploy the appropriate thing at
the appropriate time so the benefit of
dynamic stretching is it can improve
what I'll call nervous or the nerves
muscle and the connective tissue what I
mean by that is you can see improvements
in performance if you look at the
literature on this you'll see things
like dynamic warm-up improve your
maximal strength your sprinting speed
perhaps your vertical jump things like
that
if you've ever exercised before you know
exactly what I'm talking about
no one would ever set a max on their
back squat walking in cold off of the
street with no warmup you and of course
progressively build up do a little bit
more weight to get closer I have a bit
of a what's called a potentiating effect
and some other ancillary benefits of
simply increasing core temperature blood
flow etc okay so there's really no
dispute there that a dynamic warmup of
some type will enhance performance the
downside of dynamic is it's not gonna be
very good typically and actually
improving permanent changes in range of
motion or flexibility now I don't want
to confuse anyone here but I am that
proponent of getting a lot of your
changes in your your flexibility through
movements so for example I do believe
that if you do heavy dosed or fairly
heavy dose say squatting and you try to
push the end range of motion and my end
rein motion I mean in rain of your
quality of movement so right and you
start to lose position say well you work
on that enough you spent enough time in
there you're gonna see improvements in
that range of motion alright so I'm not
disputing that but the point being if
all you did for a warm-up were jumping
jacks and burpees don't expect to see
improvements in hamstring flexibility
you're not spending enough time in those
positions it's not gonna really happen
that's really what I'm going to get out
and so if we encounter someone who
simply got all the requisite mobility
and flexibility they need they can
probably jump right to dynamic warmup so
be fine but if somebody has a small or
especially a large deficit and range of
motion mobility flexibility whatever you
want to call it or whatever is the
actual issue we've got to maybe think
about adding some static stretching so
the benefit of the static is you're
gonna probably see more much more
likelihood of increasing permanent or
what I'll call chronic range of motion
we can also see that acutely and so
anyone who can say if you're a power
lifter and you start warming up and your
hips are just not there well you
continued you if you hold say go down
the bottom of a squat hold it for a
minute you come back up you'll see
increased range of motion right now
that's what I call it cute so it has an
immediate effect it'll also help you
build up range of motion and mobility or
flexibility over time okay
and we'll get into physiology of this in
a second the downside is they're going
to probably reduce perform right so what
happens is they dissipate what's called
kinetic energy now get into that a
little bit they also can inhibit or turn
off muscle spindles both of these things
are going to really result in a decrease
in performance and we see this in the
literature as well in fact it's very
well documented if you do say a
one-minute hamstring hold you're
probably going to reduce your ability to
vertical jump speed goes down squatting
strength can go down things like that
same thing if you stretched your pack or
your triceps and then did a bench
so we don't want to be holding long
stretches right before a maximal effort
performance but that doesn't mean we
don't do static stretching and that
doesn't even necessarily mean we don't
do static stretching before our workouts
we've got some things to get to here
before we get a full answer on whether
we should stretch before after or never
well let's just look at the physiology
really quickly now remember human
movement is comprised of three areas we
tend to think of human movement as a
function of muscle but that's not the
entire picture here so look at my three
different boxes the green one the blue
one and the red one and then look at the
image you can see that the box on the
left-hand side corresponds with an image
on the right hand side so the first part
of human movement is the nervous system
that's the green box so the nerve has to
come in tell a muscle to contract the
muscle has to contract it's got a
transference force from there to the
connective tissue that surrounds the
muscle that connective tissue comes
together it makes a tendon that tendon
attaches to the bone the muscle then
pulls a tendon or a connective tissue
the connective tissue pulls the tendon
tendon moves the bone you move so we
have to think about all three of these
layers or levels of human movement
nervous the nerves nervous system the
muscle itself and three the connective
tissue the ten and the ligaments and
things like that okay now I'm gonna get
I got into this in a lot more detail in
a separate video if you want to look
around and perhaps Ryan you can link
this if it's possible I don't remember
but the video I've made on how to get
stronger but not add muscle I go into I
think maybe even a half an hour or more
of the physiology of movement with
things like this so we can get more
detailed there you may have to jump
ahead in the semester if you're in class
or if you're just learning at home come
back and watch this video this film but
that's the one you want to go to okay so
that's a quick version of the physiology
now that being said there's two parts
the nervous system we got to think about
and those fall on the umbrella of what's
called proprioception if you're in
exercise science I've had these classes
before that term should ring a bell I
know you've had it an exercise
physiology but proprioception is the
idea of the nervous system understanding
where you are at in the space okay it's
got two primary branches that we
think about we're talking about
stretching branch number one is what
I'll call muscle spindles okay now these
are very inside the middle of the muscle
belly and for the most part they don't
contain a lot of act in a myosin which
means they don't contribute to
contraction there's sensory organs just
like you have a sense of smell sight
hearing you have a sense of where you're
at in space based on these muscle
spindles right sensory organs take input
in from the outside world and tell your
neurology your brainstem your brain and
spinal cord what's happening that's
exactly what muscle spindles do they
sense stretch so I'm like your old
factory frame in that sense smell tells
you what's going on in your environment
what's a wind and things around you your
muscle spindles tell your body weary if
your muscles have been stretched so
here's what happens with the muscle
spindle ok so muscle spindle will sense
a stretch imagine your hamstring is
being stretched that muscle spindles
stretch it sends information out via
gamma motor neuron so scan by motor
neurons go to your spinal cord this is
an involuntary reaction right we don't
have to go all the way to the brain and
think about this just to the spinal cord
comes back out through what are called
alpha motor neurons so any of you that
if had excess physiology you remember a
phrase that we throw on all the time and
if you any of you are taking any kind of
personal trainer or strength coach
certification I almost guarantee you
they're gonna ask about what a quote
unquote motor unit is and I know you
know the answer because it's something
you've memorized it's an alpha motor
neuron and all the muscle fibers of
innervates well that alpha motor neuron
is exactly what we're talking about so
the muscle spindles spindles it's muscle
spindle senses it's being stretched
sends information via gamma motor
neurons the gamma motoneurons go to the
central nervous system in this case is
spine and the spine sends signal back
out through them through the alpha motor
neurons and tell the muscle fibers that
are surrounding the muscle spindle to
contract this is what we call this a
stretch
shortening cycle so the hamstring is
being stretched the muscle spindles in
the hamstring sense that stretch they
send a signal to the spine spine sends a
signal back to the other muscle fibers
in your hams
and tell it to contract so the stretch
is met with the resulting shortening of
the muscle that's a cycle right this is
what keeps you from snap and this what
allows you to snap back into place so if
I were to put your arm in this position
here if I just made you relaxed it would
snap back to here that's in part because
of the muscle spindles and other part
because of the connective tissue right
but if I put you on a stretch the
default is to bring you back to this
anatomical position up here okay so the
muscle spindles in a stretch shortening
cycle is incredibly important for sport
performance is what gives us a snap a
bounce a response a quick contraction
it's very very very helpful okay now
don't worry about the the image you're
seeing here intrafusal versus ex refusal
intrafusal is a fancy way of saying
muscle spindle extra fusilar all the
fibers that are not the muscle spindle
basically okay but again a key point
muscle spindles are in the belly don't
have a lot of the muscles so deep inside
the middle they're not there for
contraction they're sensory organs
alright so if you see the image over
there you've all probably had this
happen to you but you've gone to a
physician for a physical and they've
done this knee tap test right so you
imagine sitting and I'll go back to the
image here sitting on a chair and your
knees hanging down a doctor comes in
hits your knee and your leg flicks out
right so why does that actually happen
well first of all why is the doctor
doing that why do you have to get that
done before you can play a sport well
it's because they're actually trying to
look up the nervous system in general
and in some parts your spine so they
know that this stretch learning cycle
thing happens so what they do is
actually press quickly on your patellar
tendon okay the patellar tendon you can
see from the image wraps around the
kneecap and inserts on the front of the
shin but all of your quadriceps muscles
come together to make that and turn into
that one large tendon so if I press just
below the kneecap on the patellar tendon
it stretches the quadricep over top of
the knee so the muscle spindles within
the quadricep should sense that stretch
and respond very quickly with
contraction so when I smack the bottom
of your knee there right below your knee
cap we quickly stretch the quadriceps
the quadriceps then result in a quick
contraction and your knee and your foot
flings up in the air if that doesn't
work for some reason you could have some
sort of neurological issue or spinal
cord issue going on right now some
people just don't respond that thing
very well so don't freak out but that's
what they're doing now what you also
would notice with this test is if you
tapped very lightly you wouldn't see a
response
also if you tapped hard but slowly you
wouldn't see the response either and so
the amount of stretch shortening cycle
contraction we get is in part based on
how hard it's stretched and how quickly
it's stretched we're to come back to
this concept in a little bit here but
don't forget that stress sorting cycle
is dependent upon again the level of
stretch as well as how quickly it is
stretched all right if Sony tap test
that's what that thing is all about
now the Golgi tendon organs are a little
bit different the name is directly
within the name right there they live in
the tendon so the muscle spindles live
in the muscle that GTOs holds at inner
organs limited pended and unlike
spindles where they sense stretch and
respond by contracting GTOs sense
tension and respond by telling the
muscle to stop contracting now the
common thing that we teach in class here
is from the image you can imagine it is
a sensory organ just like a spindle so
the tendon right remember to it which is
the part that connects the muscle to the
bone is gonna sense a lot of force a lot
of contraction like thinking think in
the e situation if you're doing a really
heavy muscle contraction you're trying
to pick something up and there's a lot
of force going on in the tendon and the
GTO decides this is too much I'm gonna
send a signal back to the spinal cord
and block those same alpha motor neurons
so again unlike a spindle which causes
contraction and GTO causes relaxation so
instead of stimulating the alpha motor
neurons it inhibits the alpha motor
neurons thing so you can see the little
stop octagon I've got there on the other
image and so we've got this a little bit
of a complimentary system the muscle
spindles sounds stretch and put you back
into the same spot easy example if you
were to stand on one foot
and imagine you're falling to one side
to the outside over here
the medial parts the inside of my calf
would start being stretched as I fall
this direction so as the medial part of
my calf is being stretched the muscle
spindles would activate contract and
pull me back to midline that's the point
of a muscle spindle right a GTO is a
little bit different if I were to be
stretching my calf too far here and the
GTO thought that we're in a situation
where if we continue to have force
production in this muscle something will
tear it'll stop the contraction all
right
so two different functions both a bit
protective one to put you back to
midline the other to stop you from
tearing muscle now I'll be honest with
you here I don't think that's exactly
what GTOs do in fact most research
indicates that's not actually what they
do but we'll have to come back this
later or maybe maybe best case scenario
you'll go into a deep dive and look up
GTOs what they actually function what
the research says and maybe there's
somebody out there who's a GTO expert
you can let me know send me an email or
write a comment here and correct me here
because I don't actually think that's
how they work but for the part of our
story and you know what I'm a man who
doesn't believe that the truth should
ever get and we have a good story so
we're gonna move right on okay so if we
go back to this original concept then
how does this apply to dynamic and
static stretching well I said earlier
the consequence of dynamic stretching is
it's not gonna really induce a lot of
permanent changes in range of motion why
well the flipside why does static allow
both acute so immediate and long-term
changes in range motion has this
actually happened now that we know a
little bit about the physiology of
movement let's take a look here's Mack
bar schematic well what we here's what
we know if I do some static stretching I
can see very acute changes in range of
motion very immediate and that's
probably mostly because of the nervous
system so think about let me touch your
toes right now well give it two more
seconds three more seconds you've seen
immediate improvement in your cooling
quote range of motion of your hamstrings
within seconds do you think your
hamstring muscle really got longer
hamstrings got longer and that's a no of
course they did then why are you able to
actually touch your toes you may have
seen people do things like you stand
here and just rub your hamstring or rub
a lacrosse ball on the bottom of your
foot and you immediately see an
improvement range of motion that's not
because of the muscle it's not because
of level two it's because of level one
you've got a little bit of neurology
that's holding on and this is why we can
also do fun things like rub the back of
our head or have perhaps a needle stuck
in our arm or even do breathing drills
and somehow we immediately see
improvements in range of motion well
there is a neurological component right
you can be held in neurological
positions because of stress anxiety or
other issues right so if I do static
stretching when I go to stretch my
hamstrings for example remember those
muscle spindles immediately turn on if
you stretch the hamstring it wants to
contract and fight that but after a few
seconds it realizes oh oh oh this is
intentional okay will relax and so what
happens is a couple of seconds in these
muscle spindles that are fighting you
relax and you start to gain range of
motion but remember that's coming from
you not actually gaining the range of
motion it's just you letting go of the
restriction you had it's kind of a
double negative right so you remove the
inhibitor and you're actually able to
get to that current range of motion that
you that you enjoy okay the other thing
that can happen is this now there's a
method of stretching that is very
effective called PNF proprioceptive
neuromuscular facilitation stretching so
let's take the example of the hamstrings
muscle group and let's imagine we're
doing a hamstring stretch whatever one
you like it could be the seen and hurler
stretch or whatever one you're doing now
if you were to sit there and you if you
were while you stretch it your hamstring
you flex your quad really really hard in
fact if you ever pay attention you know
that's what we're always cueing right if
you're stretching your hip flexor what
should you be squeezing your glute right
if I'm stretching my tricep we should be
flexing the opposite side so we're
always flexing the exact opposite muscle
why is that this is a good cueing thing
right
that's my quad
they're flexing my glute when I'm
searching my hamstring etc well if I
flex imagine again we're doing hamstring
stretch if I flex my quad really hard
I get more hamstring range of motion why
is that because the muscle spindles in
the hamstring are turned off when the
opposite muscles contract it's called
reciprocal inhibition body understands
on trying to contract with my quad well
in order to do that I have to let go of
my hamstring to let my quad actually
move if not I'd be stuck in an isometric
hold and so if we're trying to gain
range of motion we can trick our
neurological system to turning off the
muscle spindles by flexing the OPP's
that muscle really really hard and
that's not exactly PNF stretching but
it's a really good concept for
stretching pmf is are in this second
bullet point which is now what we would
do is we would flex that quadricep we
would get a nice big range of motion or
hamstrings and then we would start
contracting our hamstring of course let
go of the quadricep but you can flex the
hamstring 1 2 3 4 5 or whatever you want
to do 5 seconds 10 second hold something
like that where you flex the hamstring
then you relax the hamstring and you
notice oh wow I can stretch my
hamstrings farther now what happened
this contract relaxed contracts idea is
called PNF stretching and it takes
advantage of the GTOs so remember the
GTOs the hamstrings are going to sense
tension and they cause the hamstring to
relax remember they block the alpha
motor neurons so if I put a little bit
of tension in them on on purpose
activate the GTOs via the GTOs will then
block the muscle activation and cause
the muscle to relax because of that I
gain an acute range of motion so I can
use this again acutely or chronically
number one if I if I'm just needing to
get some hamstring flexibility or some
the tricep flexibility or whatever I
need I can do a little bit of stretching
prior to my workout and gain some acute
range of motion I can also use this as a
chronic stretching tool and it's fairly
effective in fact it's probably my
favorite method of stretching for that
purpose and that's working because of
what's called autogenic inhibition but
it's the same idea right you're turning
on the GTOs getting them also to relax
very good thing for honestly just
general relaxation too so if you're
trying to do some relaxation drills the
night before a big competition or you're
stressed because a finals week or
something like that to spend 10 minutes
doing a whole button is 6 minutes 3
minutes doing a whole body
PNF stretching thing autogenic
commission turn things on let it relax
gain range of motion etc so it's really
really helpful for that okay so that's
the acute side on the chronic side
here's what we probably know if you see
any improvements in a range of motion of
flexibility over the course of say hey a
month later two months later three
months later it's probably not nervous
system based right again if you fix that
if you have that issue that's kind of
just kind of get you to the level that
you normally have you gotta stop
blocking but how do you add more range
of motion well it's not gonna come from
muscle either now technically there's a
mechanism in which you can add
sarcomeres in serial line and lengthen
the actual muscle but that is a
different thing with the entire my money
and we need more research in this area
no doubt about it but my money is that
any real changes in range of motion you
have are actually coming from the
connective tissue alright and what we
know is that takes time and load so you
have to kind of hold it be in those
positions for a very long time because
remember there's no blood flow in a
connective tissue it's not something
that's really that plastic and adaptable
compared to the muscle itself and so we
have to invest a bit of time in the
connective tissue to really see changes
there but that is much easier to do than
actually lengthening the muscle itself
my estimation anyway so again and we do
need more research in this area it's not
at all clear but that's probably what
we're looking at so if we look at the
package combined static stretching is
gonna give us that nervous system
because of autogenic and reciprocal
inhibition and it's going to give us
allow us to see imprint improvements and
changes in the connective tissue itself
which will actually lead to change in
the position and so if we if we really
have an athlete or a client individual
or yourself that really actually needs
to see some changes in mobility
flexibility we don't want to eliminate
static stretching and entirely we need
to understand when to use it though so
we'll come back to our our
we'll do the inverse which was talked
about dynamic so we said the pros of
dynamic are that they can improve
performance the consequences are of
static or they can they hurt performance
so let me give you an example do me a
favor here if you're able to only to
stand up and only to perform a counter
room at jump I'll give you just a second
if you don't know what that is
stand up nice and tall get this fast you
can and jump besides you can know don't
land on anything and tear an ACL or roll
the ankle or anything but go ahead and
do one for me if you're on the ground do
an explosive jump push-up do something
real explosive movement go ahead do I'm
not I'm not kidding we're not moving on
no we're gonna stay right here and tell
all of you do it every single one of you
do it do it okay you jumped County move
it now do it one more time but do it
faster
in other words remember the muscle
spindle thing if I do a counter loomin
jump and then try to explode vs. dip and
drive the faster you dip and drive the
more muscle spindle activation we get
the higher your jump right so we're
using muscle spindles to our advantage
by putting the hamstrings and glutes on
a quick stretch we can goat or
convincers or cheat our glutes and
hamstrings into contract anything
quickly okay got that kind of movement
jump in now what I want you to do is
this stand up all the way shake it out
I'm gonna have you squat all the way
down now I would do it right now but you
would lose me on camera fact hey love it
can't let squat all the way down and
hold and now Ryan's gonna let this clock
Rhine can you if you can put a clock on
the screen here and let it run for a
minute go we're gonna hold this position
for a whole minute and you should notice
a couple of different things
hey number one as the seconds go by
state get your ass back down there I
didn't say stand up hold that squat hold
it all the way down there as the time
goes on you'll start to see an
improvement range of motion right
remember what we talked about earlier
hey you static stretch you will see a
cute range of motion brutemen
neurological systems turning
often in the words turning muscle
spindles off GTOs probably not doing a
lot here the muscle spindles are going
on you're seeing a very small in fact
may be very large improvement range of
motion
keep holding keep holding Rian you'd let
this thing run until that whole minute
comes up and at the end of this minute
we're gonna jump up as high as you can
now a couple of things before we jump do
not bounce so don't read it don't stand
up a little bit go back down then jump
won't you let go from exactly where
you're at right now
and when this one-minute clock ends
explode jump up boom now how many of you
got very high in the air probably none
of you in fact some of you probably
didn't even clear the ground now which
one these times this one or the Academy
would jump did you jump higher certainly
the one before right well why is that
why did that short bout of static
stretching although it improve range
motion why did it hurt performance well
two things number one it's actually
dissipating the kinetic energy and so
the way we create human movement it's a
three-part system nerve muscle and
connective tissue right well the nerve
is a signal the actual contraction of
force production comes from the muscle
and a connective tissue so your muscle
can contract any time you tell it to and
it has its own way to produce ATP and
energy to create force but the only
thing we can do for connective tissue
since it doesn't have actin and myosin
it doesn't have metabolism really is we
can put some energy in the system called
kinetic energy and then extract some
energy out so by putting a muscle on
stretch we start stretching connective
tissue when we start putting energy into
that system but if you hold that for
long enough that energy eventually
dissipates so then when I go to contract
I'm left with only the muscle that
contribute to force production
I mean imagine a rubber band if I held
the rubber band I pulled it back a
little bit let it go it would snap with
some force if I pulled it back on why it
was snapping a lot more force right so
more stretch more force and if I pulled
it back quickly and snapped that I would
get a big snap out of it
all right well again see the strength
video and all this
but think of the connective tissue like
a rubber band if though I pulled that
rubber band way out and then held like
that for ten years when I let it go what
happened there my band it probably
wouldn't move at all right so we lost
the elasticity or now they have that
extreme example but the same thing is
happening a smaller level where you can
lose a kinetic energy that we store up
in the connective tissue so again to
reiterate the acute stretch right if I
already panned drive the more stretch
the more force production but if I do it
for too long I lose my kinetic energy
and the faster the stretch the more
force production okay so then take a
look at something like this right you've
all seen somebody do this Oh what
happened right there let's think about
the physiology so parents going down
there he's squatting and right there
why'd he do that all right why do people
balance at the bottom we'll sit on a
bench press right come back up maybe
rebound bounce back up we see it very
kind of consistently in a squat well
what happens as you're sitting at the
bottom of that squat there we start to
lose that kinetic energy so that means
our contribution for force production
are going entirely on the muscle we're
losing all of the connective tissue but
what happens if I do that quick little
rebound uh-huh I can actually put some
energy back into that connective tissue
and I can reactivate muscle spindles
because remember when we statically
stretch like that in the muscle spindles
turn off but if I kind of shake them up
for a quick second even a half second
like that we get a little bit of
connective muscle spindle activation
again all right so should i bounce like
that well what have we learned
everything has a pro on a con right so
we got to think through it why do that
rebound we can add kinetic energy like I
said and we can reactivate the stress
sorting cycle and so now what we can
think about then is pausing
if you're familiar with strength
training and all are the sports of
weightlifting or powerlifting some
coaches will use what are called
squats or paws lips so imagine an
athlete like that they go down the
bottom and they hold four one two three
four five seconds they may rebound like
that but most of the time but it's gonna
come straight back up it's very
different than somebody who goes down at
the bottom of the control and then
explodes off the bottom or bounces even
intentionally on the bottom which one's
better well it depends on our goal right
let's think about physiology again right
so if I'm going all the way to the
bottom like that and I stop I dissipate
kinetic energy which means I rely
entirely on most if I go quickly though
I'm actually doing the opposite if I do
a quick rebound I'm relying heavily on
neurology and heavy on connective tissue
especially if I do that quick rebound at
the annual range of motion all right so
if I do a quick rebound like this like a
vertical jump I'm not really gonna
stretch the connective tissue because I
didn't really put the system on a range
of motion I'm just gonna use nervous
system but if I do a full range of
motion dunning I use a nervous system
muscle spindles and I get the connected
tissue because they're really stretched
out so it depends on our goal are we
trying to train the muscle are we trying
to train the other parts of human
movement we got to think about this
first that's our answer I don't know the
goal I can't tell you what to do so
here's some examples myself personally I
am very reactive this is what I call it
okay so if I were to do a static
vertical jump or a counter boom a
vertical jump or if I did what's called
a static so I go down and hold a quarter
squat position for three or four seconds
and then jump which one should I jump
higher with the squat and pause a static
jump or the counter roommate jump well
certainly should be the counter movement
jump right in fact almost all of us
should be it the question is how much
should they differ if say I had a
30-inch vertical with my pause and jump
and then with my counter movement I had
a 40 inch vertical well here's what that
would tell me I'm very good at getting
power and force production when I get to
use my connective tissue and the muscle
spoons and so an athlete like me I would
have benefited for a lot more pausable
because I was already very good at using
connective tissue in the nervous system
my muscles were not as strong though as
my nervous system of my connective
tissue were so if I take the nervous
system the connective tissue out of it
in other words go down and hold and stop
I force myself to improve my weakness
which in my case was the muscle spot
muscle site if you look at an athlete
who says okay did my static and I did my
counter movement and I did thirty inches
with my static and thirty one with my
counter then I would say the opposite
you need to actually develop your
connective tissue you need to develop
the muscle spindle sign of things so you
need don't pause as much I need you to
maybe add a little more bounce in there
and get a little bit more snappy a
little bit snappier if you will right
and so both are appropriate so we have
to think about this when we're thinking
about our stretching paradigm what are
we trying to do I know if I static
stretch a ton I'll lose some energy in
the connective tissue that's gonna put
more reliance on muscle that's gonna
decrease my performance but maybe if my
training goal is to take some burden off
the connective tissue put more on muscle
who cares right it's a part of my
developmental program it's I'm a
freshman in high school I don't care
about maximizing my jump now or it's
offseason about indices of were we
really trying to work for they don't
have those questions answered I can't
answer the question of static versus
dynamic right are we doing the opposite
are we close to competition are we in
the sport of powerlifting or we using
squatting to be a better football player
or soccer player or tennis player or am
i training for hypertrophy what am i
training for someone who's training for
say fat loss or health they don't
probably care if they lose 10% of power
production in training if it makes them
feel better if they get into better
range motion and that allows them to get
into a better position so they're not as
injured as much so all this stuff has to
come into context now that you
understand the physiology hopefully we
can have better answers all right so I
want to give you some real clarity here
I've got five or six take-home points
but coming back the original question
should I stretch before after or neither
now I want to see how you do here so
thanks st. Preux all the physiology can
you envision situations at least one
where it would be a good idea
to do static stretching before working
out alright so give me one time when it
would be smart to do static before
working out I'll give you one example
maybe somebody has really poor range of
motion and it's hard for them to do
anything heavy or fast without doing
some stretching beforehand because they
can't get into a good position
alright so every time they go to squat
for example since they have such poor
range of motion their hip sockets as
soon as they get to any depth they start
losing their low back position well I
don't care if they lose 5% power I'd
rather them stay in a good position so
they don't get hurt okay so in that
particular case I'd be happy to
sacrifice a little bit of fatigue or a
little bit of max force production or
sprinting speed in order to gain range
of motion and quality of movement now
I'll probably have to have a different
strategy to chronically improve their
range of motion I can't just do five
minutes of stretching before workout and
think that's gonna actually change
anything chronically but I might be
willing to sacrifice that
okay now could you give me the opposite
give me a scenario in which it would be
maybe not the best idea to static
stretch before a workout
maybe an athlete and in peak competition
probably don't want to do thirty minutes
to hamstring stretching before I try to
win the gold medal in the hundred meter
dash probably not smart idea at all
right but I wouldn't want to free it to
warm up either so in that particular
case what would I do maybe something
more like a dynamic warmup okay now I'll
give me a third scenario all right so
give me the scenario in which say you
have an athlete and it's part of their
brain and they just refuse to not
stretch before the workout the gonna
stretch no matter what you say or you
have a coach that makes you stretch how
can you fix this problem knowing that
it's gonna compromise power a little bit
my speed and force production what can
you do we actually have a couple options
number one can you increase the time
between stretching and performance now
the research is a bit unclear
it kind of depends but basically the
longer you can give between the two the
better you can restore some that kinetic
energy and that elasticity to the
connective tissue by waiting longer so
if you can do your stretching in the
morning before your night competition
you're you're probably going to be okay
and in fact you'll see a lot of athletes
that like to do this they'll do a good
stretch mobility loosen up thing in the
morning and then compete at night that's
probably fine if that's not an option
and you have to do it like right before
your workout well you can probably again
really thin research here
but I think you can probably get away
with doing some reactivation and so you
do your 15 or 20 minutes of static
stretching you kind of shut some things
off and unintentionally well instead of
just going into your squats maybe do
some hamstring activation stuff some
light fast things and get the hamstrings
to turn back on again I think you can
mitigate some of the problems or
attenuate them at least by doing a
reactivation so we need a lot of work
there it's really tough a lot of coaches
abused this activation concept but it's
getting the right idea at least all
right so to summarize everything we've
talked about so far number one
dynamic is pretty much always a good
idea to do before training number two
static is okay before training if a
couple of things number one range of
motion is incredibly poor and that is
gonna compromise safety we really don't
want that number two if you've got more
than probably 45 minutes or so between
your stretching and your performance
again the longer the better but at least
45 minutes and number three if you have
time to do some quote-unquote
reactivation work that will probably
believe behoove you before going in
performance best-case scenario though
most of the time I would say that the
general approach would be do your
dynamic movement stuff before your
workout do your workouts and then if you
need to gain the chronic range of motion
you can use that time either post
training or the day off to improve range
of motion so you can do a lot of static
stretching after your workouts to work
on your flexibility range motion and
mobility or on your an off day things
like that another thing I didn't throw
in here but we talked about briefly
maybe I should come back and make
video on this separately let me know
maybe I did enough here I don't know but
this concept of pausing versus not
pausing to intentionally train the
muscle system versus in the connective
tissue
okay so depending on what we're trying
to train for where we may intentionally
add some pausing or some holding which
is just static stretching if you will
right stock holding or we may do the
exact opposite depending on what any of
the athletes the athlete is or or the
situation on right so that's it for this
video I'm not sure I think this would be
a 25 minute or but maybe we might miss
the mark and I have to make it a short
55 minute physiology video if you
enjoyed this I I greatly appreciate your
support the best thing you can do of
course is subscribe and all that jazz
I'm the worst with marketing and stuff I
don't don't care for really at all it's
not what I'm after
but share help people I know there's a
lot of people out there who maybe had
some exercise science training and a
long time ago but now the coaches and
practitioners their personal trainers
and they would love a rebuff or be able
to learn some of the stuff a reminder so
just share it help me get the word out
in addition there's a lot of people that
are actually currently coaching that
never had the chance or couldn't afford
to go to school and this is these are
really videos for those folks so goal if
you're new to this program my real goal
is to put basically my entire university
exercise science curriculum put all that
up in these videos for free so this is
your first time I've got a ton of other
videos in this big long format that's
fifty five or twenty five minute version
or even the five members and if you just
looking for the quick answers so again I
appreciate all the support you can check
out the patreon page if you can make
contributions there if not no worries
and for those of you in my class we'll
see you tomorrow or the next day we're
gonna do some of this stuff we're gonna
get our stretch on
so thank you for the sport and then I
will see you next time
[Music]